<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise, how by the Worde of God, Christian mens almose ought to be distributed</title>
            <title>De regno Christi. Selections. English</title>
            <author>Bucer, Martin, 1491-1551.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1557</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17086</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3965</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116198</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851415</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851415</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16686</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17086)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16686)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 309:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise, how by the Worde of God, Christian mens almose ought to be distributed</title>
                  <title>De regno Christi. Selections. English</title>
                  <author>Bucer, Martin, 1491-1551.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>29, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1557?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of part of: Bucer, Martin.  De regno Christi.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf blank?.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charities --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16686:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16686:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A TREATISE, HOW BY THE WORDE OF</hi> God, Chriſtian mens Almoſe ought to Be diſtributed.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Math. VI.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>WHen thou geueſt thyne Almoſe, let not the Trompettes be blowne before the: as Hypochrites do in their Sinagoges, and Streates, to haue Praiſe of Men.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16686:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16686:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>BEcauſe in theſe days, lyke as not manie yeres ſithc, manie luſtie and ſturdie perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes be ſuffred to begge, men counterfaitinge hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible deſeaſes and infirmities, fitte by the commen ways crauinge Almoſe: dyuerſe go about Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter Haulle, and other places, with gloues, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence to gather for the mariage of poore Maidens, but in deade to haue wherwith to coople with Harlottes, or to riotte at Dice: And ſome craftie Hypocrites, no Friers in coates, but more ſubtil the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Friers in maners, under colour to relieue a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mayntain Orphanes, poore wydowes, poore Scolers, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d other, gather muche, but put all into their owne purſes, or beſtowe litle, and that after their owne Fantaſie, and not indifferentlie to euerye one as his neade requyreth, and Goddes worde preſcribeth, And ſo by all theſe meanes, and manie other, good mens charities be utterlie abuſed: <hi>I</hi> thought it uery neceſſarie, to ſetforthe in Engliſhe the mynde and opinion of the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rende Father, and Excellent clerke Maſter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne Bucer, touchinge the right geuinge and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of Almoſe, and prouiſion for the poore, declared in his boke entitled <hi>De regno Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti,</hi> made for the <hi>Moſte Bliſſed King Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde</hi> whiche, iff good people will folowe, no
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16686:3"/> doubt but all theſe kynde off ſubtile theaues ſhal bee forced to gyue ouer their occupation, And Hypochriſie it ſelf will ſchortlie loſe one of the principall fethers of hir winge. And if thei will not, let theim take heede, that whilest thei goo about with their painted Charitie to get A litle uayn glorie, thei purchace theim ſelfs at length, by maynteninge the Lewde, euerlaſtinge dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. But <hi>I</hi> haue <hi>A</hi> good hope, that manie erre by ignoraunce, who beinge rightlie inſtructed, will ſhewe theim ſelfs conformable to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des will, and do as he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundethe: wherbye thei may fynde at length his mercifull fauor.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Fare well.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16686:3"/>
            <head>THE ORDER OFF THE prouiſion for the poore.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LMYGTIE</hi> God that ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth up the Humble, and pulleth downe the Proude, that gyueth richeſſe, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d taketh it away, plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie commaundeth his people, that thei ſhulde not ſuffer any to lacke emonge theim. Whiche commaundement the primatyue Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Chriſte at Hieruſalem kept with all reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and deuotion: wherbie there was ſuche a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundaunce of Almeſe geuen by Good men, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued eueryemans neceſsitie, and ſo emonge theim there was not one, that was not prouided for. Afterwarde, that this prouiſion and gatheringe for the poore might be the better loked unto, and contynew, the Apoſtelles inſpired with the hollie goſte, by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the hole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation, appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to that Ministerie ſeuen Men of honest re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte and fame, full of the hollie goſte, and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, on whom thei layde their handes, for a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of their admiſsion. And ſo this ordenaunce and prouiſion for the poore was uery deuoutlie obſerued, till Antichriſt with his fluddes of wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, ouerflowed the Churche of Chriſt. Thoſe that were called to that hollie ministerie, were named the <hi>Deacons</hi> of the Churche: who albeit thei ought to be aſsistaunt to the Elders of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16686:4"/> Congregation, in the conſeruation and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Diſcipline of Chriſte, and the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacramentes: yet their chief Office and duetie was, to kepe the names of the <hi>poore</hi> in the Congregation of the Chriſtians, to knowe euerye mans lif, and behauiour, And of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Almoſe of the faithfull, to diſtribute to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye one, aſmuche as was ſufficient for his neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie relieffe. For thoſe that may gette their lyuinge by their labour and trauayl, and wil not, ought to be put out of the Churche: <hi>He that do the not labour, let him not eate,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtell. Sith then it is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of god, to relieue the <hi>poore</hi> and neadie, and to ſee that none lacke: all ſuche as mynde fullie to receaue the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſte, ought to labour ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlie, that this ordenaunce be restored in to Chriſtes Churche. For thoſe that haue the goodes of the worlde and ſee their Brethern lacke, and haue not compaſsion on theim: the loue of good dothe not dwell in theim, and ſo alſo neither the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſte is in theim.</p>
            <p>And all thoſe that heare Chriſte, and the hollie goſte, wil indeuour and laboure to orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and do all good thinges in ſuche order and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner, as thei knowe the lorde, and the hollie goste hathe appoynted.</p>
            <p>And ſith it is manifeſt, that god earnestlie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badde,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16686:4"/> that his people ſhoulde ſuffer eny to beg emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge theim, and that his goodnes alſo ordeyned, that the poore ſhoulde be loked unto by certayn choſen men in the Churche, and that good mens deuotions ſhoulde be diſtributed to euerye nedie perſone, as his neceſsitie requireth: it is with out all doubt, that all thoſe pray with out deuotion, <hi>Let thy Kyngdom come,</hi> which to their power, do not beſtowe all their endouour, that this maner of prouidinge for the poore, be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in to the Churche, whiche the lorde him ſelf commaunded, and the hollie goſt in the prymyti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue churche ordayned.</p>
            <p>By the whiche meanes it ſhalbe preuented, that theſe wicked Begginge houſes, and ſubtiltie off Hypocrites, ſhall not take from thee nedie men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres of Chriſt, the Almoſe that is due to theim: nor Ambition of mans praiſe, and thanckes, nor uayne glorie, ſhall defile the right office of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſe, whiche euell how muche it ought to be eſchued, Chriſt uery playnlie taught, when he commaunded, <hi>ſo to geue Almoſe, as the left hande may not knowe, what the right hande dothe.</hi> This may best be doone, if eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man put into the Comen Chest, or Boxe of the Churche, to the uſe of the poore, aſmuche as he may ſpare of that God geueth him. For when euery man him ſelf will diſtribute his owne Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſe,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16686:5"/> friſt the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of the hollie gost, and the lawfull <hi>Communion,</hi> Compainie, and Fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowſhip of Saintes is broken. Beſydes thalmoſe due to the litle ones of Chriſt, and ſo to Chriſt him ſelf, is gyuen oftener to the unworthie, then to the worthie (for euerye man can not knowe and trie ſuche poore people as he meeteth ſodenlie) and alſo ſuche as be not meete to haue Almoſe, come better inſtructed to beg, yea, as it were to wringe out the Almoſe of <hi>A</hi> mans Purſe with paynted wordes, then thoſe to whom it onlie ought to be geuen. Moreouer when <hi>A</hi> man geueth Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſe with his owne hande, he dothe hardlie put out of his mynde the deſyre of mens tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ckes and uayne prayſes, which uaine rewarde when he receaueth of men: he may not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eke for the true and perfet rewarde of god. And fynallie, when it is most certein, that ſuche as gyue theim ſelfes wilfullie to the trade of Begginge, be geuen and bent to all myſchieff: what other thinge do thei that nouriſhe theim, then maynteyne and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce the greatest Pestilences and deſtructions off <hi>A</hi> commen welthe? Wherfore all ſuche as haue wiſelie writen how commen welthes ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be well gouerned, haue thought that ſuche perſones were not to be ſuffred in <hi>A</hi> comen we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lthe. And certaynlie men ought to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and lament when this right maner of proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16686:5"/> for the pore is restored in manye contrays, whiche yet be under Antichrist: ſuche as uaunte thei haue receaued the Goſpell of Christe, and profeſſe to be off his Kingdom, be ſlacke to resto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re it, yea be hynderers off it, ſeinge it is an orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of Christes Religion ſo neceſſarie, and ſo holſom.</p>
            <p>To conclude, who ſo euer dothe not carefullie endeuour, aſmuche as he may, to restore this hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie ordenaunce off the Prouiſion for the poore, as the lorde hathe commaunded, and the hollie gost ordayned: He dothe playnlie beare witnes off himſelf, that he dothe not in deade knowe, nor perfetlie deſyre Chriſte, and his Kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſo euer in wordes he boast of Christe, and his Kyngdom.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE MEANE TO RESTO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in to the Churche the right kynde of geuinge, and diſtribution of Almo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, and Prouiſion for the poore.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T</hi> is most requyſite, that all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and Gouernours, that deſire the promotion of the King<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom off Christe, and the welthe of thoſe thei gouerne, do procure
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16686:6"/> that this godlie prouiſion for the Poore and nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die bee restored, euen as the Hollie Goſte hath ſet forth unto us in the Seconde, Fourth, Fyfth, and Sixth off the Actes off the Apoſtells. For with out it, ther can bee no true felowſhip or Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off Saintes. This may be don after this ſorte, First that euerye Churche haue his Deacons, for the prouiſion, and ouerſight of the Poore, (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is ſaid,) Men off good reporte, and full off the Hollie Goste, and wiſdom, and ſo manie of theim as the multitude off the People, and off the Poore ſhall requyre.</p>
               <p>Their Office is conteyned in theſe poynies. First thei ought to make diligent ſerche, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie poore in deade bee in euery Congregation, that ought to be prouided for by the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For it belongeth to all Congregations off Christe, not onlie not to mayntayne lewde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones in their wycked Idleneſſe: but alſo to bannyſh theim their companie, who, when thei may by their owne honest labour mayntaine them ſelf, will not labour, but lyue inordinat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie conſuminge the ſustenaunce, that is due to the neadie and Poore off Chriſte. And agaynst ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che perſones this Rule is to be kept, <hi>He that laboreth not, let hym not eate:</hi> That com, maundement alſo off the Hollie Goste towchin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge Wydowes, ought to be expounded alſo off all
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16686:6"/> neady. Iff ther bee any faithfull man or woman, ſaith the Hollie Goste, that hathe wydowes, let him prouide, and minister unto theim: and let not the Congregation be burdened, that thei, whiche are right wydowes may haue inough. So lykewiſe thoſe, that haue anye neadie under theim, whether thei be their kynsfolkes, ſeruaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, or otherwiſe ioyned to theim by any ſpeciall cauſe, ought to mynyster to ſuche perſones ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries for their lyuinges, if thei be able to do it, and to ſpare the Congregation, as it may be the better able to mayntayne and keepe thoſe, that haue no kynſfolkes, maſters, or friendes, that will, or can prouide for theim.</p>
               <p>All mens myndes ought to be moued with this fearefull Iudgement off the Hollie Goste: <hi>Iff ther be any man, that dothe not prouide for his owne, and ſpeciallie for theim off his howſholde: The ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me hath denied the faithe, and is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe then an Infidell.</hi> For unto thoſe, that God hathe by any ſpecyall meanes ioyned togither, this the ſeconde principall commaundemaunt, wherin all the lawe is conteyned and fulfilled, dothe chieflie belonge: <hi>Thou ſhalt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue thy neighbour as thy ſelffe.</hi> For tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, whom God coupleth and ioyneth to gither by the Bande off kyndred, affinitie, howſolde,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16686:7"/> or any other particuler meanes: he maketh theim therbie, aboue all other, neighbours.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> The first poynt then off the Office of the Dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the poore, is, that thei make dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſerche, who lacke in deade, and be not able to relieue their owe lacke: Then who counterfaite <hi>A</hi> nedde, or with Idleneſſe and Riot, make themſelfes nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: And finalie, who haue ſuche neibours, that can, or do take the care to prouyde for theim.</p>
               <p>Suche as the Deacons ſhall fynde, that neither can gette their owne lyuinge, nor haue off their neighbours, that doo relieue theim: their Names, with the maner off their neade and behauiour, thei ought to write in <hi>A</hi> particular boke, And certayn tymes to uiſite theim, and to call theim unto theim, that thei may the more certanlie kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we, how well and uertuouſlie they uſe thalmoſe of Good People, and what thinges from tyme to ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, thei neade. For as nothing will ſuffice the wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cked and lewde, neather haue thei any meaſure or truthe in begginge: ſo the Good and ſhamefast do couer and diſſemble their neade, and thinke euerie thinge to muche, that is geuen unto theim by the Congregation. But the Hollie Goste ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the appoynted and ordened the maner and ende off Diſtribution of Almes, that none ſhoulde lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, and euerye one ſhoude haue aſmoche as is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for his honest relieff. And who cannot
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16686:7"/> ſee euen by this one thinge, How neceſſarie it is for Congregations to haue ſuche Deacons for the poore: that not raſhlie, but moſt diligentlie ſearche out, and certaynlie knowe the ſtate off euery one that aſketh the helpe off the Congregation: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and what thinge he lacketh, and how moche is to be gyuen to euerye one for his neceſſarie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieff. Beſydes, whether thei haue any Freendes, that be able and ought to relieue theim. For ſuche ought by the Congregation to be forced to relieue their owne: and theru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to, as in thexecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off the rest off the diſcipline, the Deacons ought to be aſsiſtence to the miniſters off the worde, and Elders.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> 
                  <hi>Thother</hi> poynt off thoffice off Decons is, to keepe what ſo euer commeth to the Churche, for the uſe off the poore, and therof to diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to euerie one that neadeth, aſmoche as ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice to lyue <hi>A</hi> godlie liff in the lorde: And to keepe <hi>A</hi> perfecte accoumpt off their doinge, Whiche thei must yelde to the miniſters off the woorde, and the Elders: <hi>Procuringe,</hi> after the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple off the Apostell. <hi>Honeſt thinges not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie before God, but alſo in the ſight off all men.</hi> Wherfore the Hollie Gost requyrith that ſuche Deacons ſhoulde be off Good reporte emonge the people off Chriſte. For as Men bee deſyrous off Money: ſo upon the leaſt occaſion,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16686:8"/> thei ſuſpecte euell off ſuche as haue the diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion off commen money. Beſydes, the poore that haue not lerned, by the ſprite off Christe, to be contented, whether thei haue plentie, or do ſuffer neade, be uery ſuſpitious, and full off complayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. And therfor that ſuche Deacons ſhoulde be of the greater authoritie emonge the people of God, and the better credite geuen unto theim: the auncient Churches appoynted unto theim, the next degree after the Elders. And admitted theim to be Aiders in the hollie mynyſterie of thadmini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtration, bothe of the worde, and alſo of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes. Antichriſt made this office, as he dyd all other Mynyſteries, nothinge at all, but to ſerue for a uaine pompe: as at this preſent day ther bee uery fewe that thinke the Deacons office to be any other thinge, then to ſerue the Buſshops, and Prieſtes at Maſſe, and to reade the goſpell whiche thinges were appointed to this office onlie at the firſt, that whileſt thei prouided for the poore, and dyd helpe to execute the diſcipline, thei ſhulde be of the greater Authoritie, and haue the more cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dite emonge the people off God. <hi>For</hi> the ouerſight of the poſſeſsions belonginge to Churc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hes, and to gather the fruytes, reuenues, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of thoſe thinges that were gyuen for the relief of the poore: certayn were appointed, who we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re called Subdeacons and Bailiffes, that the Dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cons
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16686:8"/> might firſt gyue theimſelfes to the right di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuche thinges, as were gathered for the relief of the poore, ſo as euerie one might haue that was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in deede to lyue to the lorde: then to ſee that thoſe that were relieued by the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>grega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dyd lyue to ſerue God: And finallie, to furder this Diſcipline emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge other Chriſtians, whoſe life a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d behauour thei ought the better knowe a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d trie, by the reaſon of gatheringe relief for the poore. This ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and maner of gatheringe and diſtributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Deacons, and Subdeaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, was obſerued till and in the tyme of Gregorie the Buſshop of Rome, as appereth in manye his Epiſtells. <hi>And</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the Deaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Churche be neuer ſo honeſt, and wiſe: yet can thei not prouide for the Poore, onles thei haue wherwith to diſtribute to the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ore, and therfor it belongeth to Magiſtrates to ſee, that Churches haue ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to relieue the poore. In tyme longe paſt, the Fourth parte of all Reuenu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es, that either belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged to the Spiritualtie, by their Poſſeſsions, or cam to hit by good mens gyſts, and oblations, was taken for the relief of the poore. Beſydes, manie uertuous Princes, and good Men made Hoſpitals, and howſes for the Relief off the poore: Some for ſuche as were Hole of bodye, and ſome for ſuche as were ſicke: So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to keepe Infantes, and ſome to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte Straungers, and Baniſshed me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But all theſe in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynuaunce of tyme, through the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16686:9"/> wycked Monkes, and Pryeſtes, were conuerted from thoſe godlie uſes, and turned to the maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of their owne bellies, Pleaſures, and pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Thei paſſed neither of the Fownders good myndes, nor the lawes of Magiſtrates: but blyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded poore men, makinge theim beleue, that more profiet ſhoulde comme bothe to quycke and ded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, if thoſe godlie Almoſe were beſtowed on Maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, and ſuche like ungodlie Triſſhe traſſhe: then iff Chriſte therwith ſhulde be fedde, in the Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: refreſſhed in the Thyrſtie: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted with lod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginge in Straungers, and the Harbourleſſe: clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in the Naked: and uiſited in the Sicke, and Enpriſoned. Wherfore, it is the parte off good Magiſtrates, to prouyde, that ſuche thinges be brought to their right uſes. And beſydes, it is con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that ſome Taxes be ſet on riche ſpirituall Promotions, for the relieff off the Pore: in ſteede off the Fourthe parte off their Reuenues, whiche by ſo manye Canons was lymeted to the uſe of the Poore.</p>
               <p>Morouer lest thoſe, that be not worthie to haue the Almoſe of the Churche, and of good men, ſhoulde take it from thoſe that be worthie, and in deade neadie: Good Magiſtrates ought to renue, and put in execution, that lawe off God, and off the Emperour Valentynyan, whiche forbiddeth, that any man be ſuffred to begge: and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16686:9"/> that thoſe that be able to labour, ſhoulde be forced to labour: and that ſuche as be not able to labour, ſholde be kept as our Brethern, and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres, euerye one in the Congregation where he dwelleth. And that this may bee the better doon, commaundement ought to be gyuen, that euerye man maintaine ſuche as be of his one howſolde, or other wiſe properlie ioyned to him, if he be able: And that euery Citie, Towne, and uillage, doo mayntain ſuche poore people, as their friendes be not able to keepe, and not ſuffer theim to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der abrode. And becauſe it may be, that ſome Towne, or uilage is ſo poore, that it is not able to relieue al the Poore therof: that ſuche alſo be not left unprouided, it is uery requyſite, that in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Shire, certayne godlie, and ſpirituallie wiſe men, be appoynted: who may ſende ſuche poore people from the places where thei cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued, to ſuch Congregations, where thei may be ſufficientlie relieued. For all we Christians be togither membres, by the which name, the Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregations off the Gentiles in the tyme off Saint Paule, and at his exhortation, dyd confeſſe, that it was their duetie, to relieue the Congregations in Iurie, that ſuffered great hunger and famine. Furdermore, becauſe through our corrupte, and always diſobedient nature to God, we contynu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>allie lothe the ordinaunces, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16686:10"/> off God, and after our owne luste, and fond iudgement, we deſire to folowe other meanes, and waies, then God hathe appoynted: ther wilbe ſom, that, not withſtandyng this most holy prouy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion for the poore, will not put their Almoſe in to the comen cheſte, or boxe off the lorde, but will rather geue their Almoſe with ther owne ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, if they be mynded to geue any at all. Such mens pride muſt be mette with, not onely by a lawe off the Magiſtrat, but alſo by the diſcipline off the Churche. By a lawe, to make theim geue double to the lordes Cheſte, if they be founde to geue any thynge pryuatlie to the neadie: And by the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Churche, that if any geue nothing in to the lordes cheſte, he be warned off his duetie by the mynyſters off the Churche, accordyng to the worde off God. Whoſe admonytion if they ſtubbournlie conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, that they be taken for Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nykes, and Publicans. For albeit, it be left to euerie mans will, to offer to Christ his lorde, to thuſe off his litle ones, aſmoche off his goodes as he will: yet no man maye be ſuffred, contrarie to the expreſſe commaundement of God, to come al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways with an <hi>Emtie hande</hi> into the preſence off the lorde, and utterlie to deſpiſe the ordenaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce off the holy Gost, for the prouiſion for the poore, yea, aſmoche as in hym lieth, to ſubuert it, by his pryuat diſtribution off Almoſe.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:16686:10"/>
               <p>And here wil mans wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (wich alwaies uaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it ſelf aboue Goddes) obiecte, that it is unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, that mens ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des ſhulde be ſhut to the faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful, that they may not geue, at their pleaſure, to ſuch, as thei perceaue in deade to lack. For a man ſhall fynde emong the pouertie, uery good men, who be aſshamed to aſke the Almoſe off the Chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, haue they neuer ſo great neade. Herunto this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to be anſwered, first, that no mans hande is ſo ſhutte by this lawe, but that he maye open it to whatſoeuer pore he wil, and is able: but by this lawe, accordyng to Goddes commaundement, and the ordenaunce off the holy gost, this is preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the children off God maye not geueth the Enemies of Christ, theſe that either lacke not, or els be wilfullie in neade, thoſe thinges, that thei owe to the litle ones off Christ, which lacke in deade. For it is not poſsible, as I ſaied before, that any pryuat man, ſhulde ſo certeynlie ſerche out the diſpoſition off the poore, as thoſe, that be appoynted to that office by the Churche, and dailie be exerciſed with all diligence therin.</p>
               <p>And God doth not keepe his giftes, and encrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce off his holy ſprite, from ſuch, as he hathe cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and called, to ſo great mynyſteries of his chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che. Beſides, admit, that euery man knowe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynlie his neadie neighbours: yet is it far better, that euery man ſende ſuch poore people, that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16686:11"/> his relief, be they neuer ſo holy and uertuous, to the Deacons off the Churche, to receaue off theim: For otherwiſe, others ſhal take example by him, to diſtribute alſo their owne Almoſe, and ſo oftentymes to ſuch as they knowe not, and be not worthye off Christes Almoſe, who can beg more boldelie and craftelie, then the Poore in dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. We ought to take wonderful heade, lest the least hole in the worlde be opened to our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural pride, to be wiſe agaynst God, and to ſwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue a heare breadeth from his commaundementes and ordenaunces, either to the right hande or to the lefte. Iff any be aſshamed to go gladlye to the hole companye and mynyſterie off the Deacons, let him declare his pouertie to one of the Deacons: or if he be lothe to do this, then let ſuch as knowe his neade, and godlynes, ſhewe it to the Deacons, and get neceſſarie relief for him.</p>
               <p>Not with ſtandyng, no Christen man, be he fal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>len from neuer ſo great richeſſe to pouertie, from neuer ſo high degree to the loweſt, ought to be aſshamed of the Croſſe off Christ, and the hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſom remedie, that God hath prouyded: moche leſſe ought Christen men be lothe, to receaue relief off their neade, at the Lordes hande, by the mynyſterie off his Churche, by whoſe most iust, and no leſſe holſom Iudgement for theim, they be come to ſuch pouertie, and baſe degree of life. Howbeit, it perteineth to the Deacons office, not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16686:11"/> onelie to haue reſpect to euerie mans pouertie, but alſo off the weakenes off their myndes, and with ſuch wiſedom, and liberalitie, to helpe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie mans neceſsite, that they laie on no man troub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led with pouertie, the trouble alſo off ſhame: nor that they bryng any, that haue in tyme paſt been wel and liberalie maynteyned, to ſuch ſcarcitie and ſkantnes off meate and clothyng, as they bee not able to ſuffer, albeit ſuch relief were ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, to an other that hathe ben ſo uſed.</p>
               <p>The commaundement off the Holy Gost ought in this poynt to be conſidered, that ther be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moche geuen to euerie one, as is neceſſarie to lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de a good, and godlie life. And it is manyfest, that as all men be not off like ſtrength off bodie, nor haue not ben brought up after one kynde off liuing ſo ſome ought to haue more, ſome leſſe: ſome fyner, ſome courſer, meate, apparel, and other ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſaries. Which thyng Seynt Gregorie conſide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryng, when the noble men, and women were ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led by the Lombardes, he gaue unto them uery li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral Pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſions for their relief, of the goodes of the church. And therfore Chriſtian Magiſtrates ought to make this lawe, Firſt, that no man be ſuffred to beg: but that euerie man do maynteyne, and kepe his owne houſeholde, kynred, and allies, if he be able to do it: the iudgement wherof, ought to per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teigne to the ordynarie Magistrat. And that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16686:12"/> ſuch as be deſtitute off ſuch helpe, be m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> by the Citie, towne, uil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge, or Congregation whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re they dwell. If any citie, towne uilage, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation, be not able to, maintaine the pouertie ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, that then, by the diſcretion of the chief Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treye, ſuch poore people be ſent to ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> richer Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where thei may be relieued.</p>
               <p>Another poynt of this lawe ought to be, for the election, and appoyntyng off Deacons, as is afore ſeid, and that they be, by their othe, enioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, diligentlie to ſerche out, what thinges euery man neadeth, and that they faithfully, to their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, geue it to theim: and to make an accompte of their receiptes, and paymentes, to the mynyſters of the worde, and Elders.</p>
               <p>The third poynt, that it be forbodden to geue Almoſe priuatlie, and that all men be exhorted, that they will rather, according to Goddes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, and the ordenaunce of the holy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>host, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt their Almoſe to the Churches, and to the mynyſters appointed for that purpoſe: then after their own natural pride, diſtribute it theim ſelfs, contrarie to goddes worde, and the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Hollie Goste.</p>
               <p>The fourth point, that thei cauſe to be reſtored, for the relief of the poore, ſuch giftes as wer offred, by our Elders to Chriſte, if any yet remayne.</p>
               <p>And the fewer off thoſe giftes ſhal be founde re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maynyng:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16686:12"/> the greater penſions to be ſet on riche benefices, for the relief of the poore, in recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe off the fourth parte off the Reuenues off all Churches, that is due by ſo many Canons.</p>
               <p>The fyfte point, that great paynes be ſet on theim, that ſhall blaſpheme this most holy Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion off the Holie Goste, or that ſhall go about to pul any man from it. And if any man ſhall thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke any thing to be corrected in the Deacons, and the prouiſion for the poore, that he first warne the Deacons therof: and if they will not folowe his reaſonable warnyng, that he declare the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier to the mynyſter of the word, and the Elders: that in all thinges, the Authorite of Goddes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de maye be of force, and the wicked pride of men, who can allowe nothing that is ordeined of God, maye be reſiſted in euerie place, and in tyme: and ſo it maye be the eaſlier obteyned off the people off Christ, wherby the litle ones off Christ maye ſo liberallie be prouided for, as we maye at length ioifullie heare: Come ye bliſſed of my father, and receaue the Kingdom, that is prepared for you, from the begining of the worlde. <hi>I</hi> was hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, and ye gaue me to eate &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And it is not ynough for the liberalitie of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians, to geue onely meate, harbour, and clothing to ſuche as be in extreme neceſsite: but alſo they ought liberallie to geue of the giftes, God hathe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16686:13"/> geuen theim, wherwith godly maydens mariable, who for lack of dowrie remayne long unmaried, maye be in tyme maried, and coupled with honeſt men, and alſo that wittie Children, that lack fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, may be brought up to ſtudie, to ſerue in Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes Churche. Beſydes, good Chriſtians, that lack wherwith to exerciſe their craftes, may be therwith holpen, partlie by gifte, parlie by loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, as ther may come profet of their Arts, and thei maye be the better able to nouryſh, and bring up their children for the lorde, and to make theim profetable membres of the comen welthe. For it is not ynough for the Congregations off Chriſt to prouyde, that men may onlie lyue, but that thei may lyue to the Lorde, for a certeyn and mutual profet betwene them ſelfs, and of the Churche, and commen welthe. And therfore all Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations ought to prouyde, that all thoſe that be baptized in Chriſte, be uertuouſlie brought up from their childehod, and taught good Artes, that euerie one, accordyng to his portion, may bryng forth ſomwhat, to profet the comen wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, and to declare hymſelf to others a true, and profetable membre off Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="addition">
               <head>An addition.</head>
               <p>Ther be, that denye not the office off the Dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>conrie in the Churche of Christ, to be ordeyned
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16686:13"/> by God: but ſaye, ſuche office is not of neceſsitie. For ther be ſom Congregations, where al men be welthie, and ther is no Pouertie, and ſo no neade of the Deaconrie. That it pleaſeth theim ſo gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely to graunt, thoffice of the Deaconrie to be the ordenaunce of God, they deſerue no tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes. For if they ſhulde denye it, they muste other con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe, Seynt Paule erreth, or ſeynt Paule wolde ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ye, they erre. For, beſydes he teacheth what men ought to be called to be Deaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che of Chriſt, he ſaieth playnelye, that God ordey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned and conſtituted in his Churche: firſt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels, ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>darilie Prophetes, thirdlie Teachers, then thoſe that do myracles: after that, thoſe that haue the giftes of healing, helpers, gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and diuerſitie of tongues. Vnder wich na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of Helpers, as a general word for al men that may do good in the Churche of Christ, thoffice of the Deacons (according as the interpretours on that place agreablye do teſtifie) as it is in the Actes mencioned, is conteyned. Now where they ſaie, ther may be a Churche without poore, and ſo no neade of Deacons: ſo may it be ſaid, ther may be a Congregation, wherin all may bee ler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned in Goddes worde, and therfore no neade of preachers and teachers. But what a fonde kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of argument is it, to reaſon of thinges, that maye be, as though they were? to alledge thinges
<pb facs="tcp:16686:14"/> that be onelie in <hi>Vtopia,</hi> as if they wer commen in euerie Contrey: to magnifie their owne uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyn Sophiſtrie, and to neglect the certeyn doctri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of God? who forſeyng all thinges, aſwel to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me as preſent, ſaied, ye ſhall haue alweis poore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, and therfore ordeyned this mynyſterie in his Churche of neceſsitie, not for a tyme, but for euer to contynue: to haue the ouerſight, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re off the poore, becauſe ther ſhalbe poore for euer. And albeit God, in ſom particular congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, dothe ſo beſtowe his benefites, as many be ritche, and fewe poore: yet wil he not, that they ſhal haue their reſpecte, onelie to the poore in the ſame Congregation, but alſo to ſuch as be in other Congregations, as appeareth by thoſe of Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia, Achaia, and Corinthus. Who, accordyng to the doctrine off ſeynt Paule, and their duetie, ſent their charitie to Hieruſalem, for the relief of the ſayntes, and poore Brethern there. Some ayen ſaie, why may not euery man appoint his owne Al mener, or Chamberer, to diſtribute his Almoſe, ſo the poore be prouided for, it forceth not, how, or by whom it be don?</p>
               <p>Albeit this obiection be before ſufficientlie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, by Master. <hi>D.</hi> Bucer: yet it may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that ſuch obiections procede off affection and pryuat gaigne (which maye doo moche with worldlie men) and not of a zeale to aduaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce Goddes glorie.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:16686:14"/>
               <p>For Chriſtian men, that ſeeke to ſerue god their lorde and Master, and not their owne commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and affections, when thei knowe his will, plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, and ordenaunce, ſerche no further: but as good ſubiectes, and ſeruauntes, by all meanes la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to do, and fulfil the ſame.</p>
               <p>They diſpute not, why God hathe ordeyned, or commaunded this, or that: nor thynke this myght be other wiſe don, then God hathe deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: or that he hathe don, is not off neceſsitie.</p>
               <p>They knowe his wil, and pleaſure, declared by his worde, is an unchaungeable lawe, wherunto nothyng maye be added, or dymynyſshed, but ought to be obeied off all his ſeruauntes: that he hathe made nothyng in uayne, but as he is the uery wiſedom it ſelf, and forſeeth what is beſt for his: ſo hathe he moſt wiſelie, and most neceſſarilie or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned this mynyſterie off the Deaconrie in his Churche. Yea, they be most certeyn, that as ther be in mans bodie diuers me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, not all of one ſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, but ſom more profetable, then ſome, and yet al requyſite, and neceſſarie to make a parfet bodie: ſo in the Churche of Chriſt, ther be dyuers mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres, mynyſteries, and uocations, preachours, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>achours, elders, deacons &amp;c. Who, albeit they be not off like Authorite, and degree: yet be they all requyſite, and neceſſarie to the edifiyng off a godlie, and parfet Churche off Chriſte.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:16686:15"/>
               <p>Neither will any of Chriſtes ſeruauntes, thruſt hymſelf, not beyng lefully called, into any myny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſterie, or ſeake to come into it by the wyndowe, as Theues and murderers do, but wil tary til he may enter by the doore, til he be ordinarilie cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led by the Churche off Christ, as Stephen, and the reſt off the Deacons in the prymytiue Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che were. For all good men wil feare, leſt when thei either do any thing contrarie to Goddes or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>denaunce, or medle with that, wherunto they be not ordynarilie called, the plage off God will fal on them, as it dyd uppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the like, by iuſte iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, in tyme past. Nadah, and Abiu the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Aaron, toke thier Cenſers, put a ſtraunge fier therin, and offred to God: but becauſe thei dyd it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to the ordinaunce of god, the fier cam from the lorde and deſtroid them. Vſa, becauſe he ſet his hande to ſtaie up tharke of the lorde, that it ſhould not fal, albeit the deede ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie conſidered was good, yet becauſe he medled with that office, wherunto he was not ordyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilie called, and appoynted, God plaged him with death. Kynge Ozias, becauſe he wolde be buſie in other mens uocation, offryng incenſe to the Lordes which perteined to the miniſterie of the Children off Aaron, and not to his, was stroken with the Leprie. The wiſeman ſaith in the prouerbes, Ther is a waie that ſeameth to a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16686:15"/> man iust and right, but thende bryngeth to dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. When men leaue the waies of God, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie their buſie braynes about thinges beſides, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to Goddes worde, they fal at length clene from God, and become Godleſſe. Therfore Men ought to take heade, and to leaue their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certeyn phantaſies, and cleaue unto the certeyn worde of God, wheru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to whoſoeuer leaneth, can not ſtumble, whoſoeuer foloweth it, cannot erre: and he that walketh therin, ſhal at length come to the eternal Kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is prepared for all ſuch as loue and folowe God.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Remembre the poore, and God wil reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber you:</l>
                  <l>Forget the poore, and God will not forget you.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
